<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Martin Sterchi</title>
<link>https://martinsterchi.ch/news/</link>
<atom:link href="https://martinsterchi.ch/news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.8.26</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>New Publication Out</title>
  <dc:creator>Martin Sterchi</dc:creator>
  <link>https://martinsterchi.ch/news/data_in_brief/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Together with my colleagues Emily Raubach and Lorenz Hilfiker, I have published a new paper in the Elsevier journal <em>Data in Brief</em>. The article presents the different network representations that I previously introduced on my blog. The journal’s purpose is to make research datasets accessible to the community by providing the data as well as documentation and metadata in a clear and structured way.</p>
<p>In our paper, we describe the four network representations in detail, explain how the raw data were processed to construct them, and provide some initial descriptive analyses. Our hope is that this work will make the datasets more useful to others and encourage their application in a variety of research contexts.</p>
<p>We also plan to build on these datasets in our own future work. One direction we are particularly excited about is combining the networks with a metapopulation disease model for Switzerland. For some time, I have wanted to explore whether the effect of public transportation on the spread of the flu through the country can be measured.</p>
<p>Full citation:</p>
<p>Sterchi, M., Raubach, E., Hilfiker, L. (2025). <strong>SwissRailNet: Four representations of a spatially embedded railway network dataset</strong>. <em>Data in Brief</em>, 63, 112266. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.dib.2025.112266" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.dib.2025.112266</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Publications</category>
  <guid>https://martinsterchi.ch/news/data_in_brief/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://martinsterchi.ch/news/data_in_brief/Network_SoSta.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="93" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>NetSci 2025</title>
  <dc:creator>Martin Sterchi</dc:creator>
  <link>https://martinsterchi.ch/news/netsci25_poster/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>My colleague Lorenz Hilfiker and I attended this year’s NetSci conference in Maastricht, NL. We were pleased to present our preliminary work on GNNs for the source detection problem as a poster and to receive valuable feedback from the NetSci community.</p>
<p><img src="https://martinsterchi.ch/news/netsci25_poster/FotoNetSci25.jpg" height="600"></p>
<p>Besides enjoying the conference, we also had a chance to explore Maastricht a bit. Here are some impressions:</p>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout-ncol="2">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://martinsterchi.ch/news/netsci25_poster/Maastricht1.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://martinsterchi.ch/news/netsci25_poster/Maastricht4.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://martinsterchi.ch/news/netsci25_poster/Maastricht3.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://martinsterchi.ch/news/netsci25_poster/Maastricht2.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Feel free to download our poster: <a href="Poster_NetSci25.pdf" download="">Poster (PDF)</a>. We hope to publish a paper soon.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Conferences</category>
  <guid>https://martinsterchi.ch/news/netsci25_poster/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://martinsterchi.ch/news/netsci25_poster/image.PNG" medium="image"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>First blogpost</title>
  <dc:creator>Martin Sterchi</dc:creator>
  <link>https://martinsterchi.ch/news/blog/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I’ve started a blog right here on this website (<a href="../../blog/index.html">see here</a>). I know the internet is already overflowing with blogs and other content, and the world certainly wasn’t waiting for yet another person eager to share their thoughts.</p>
<p>But honestly, this blog is, above all, a creative outlet for me. Writing my first post was a lot of fun, and if others find it interesting—great! If not, no hard feelings. 😉</p>
<p>That said, this first post took a surprising amount of work (a full workday, if we’re being honest—don’t tell my boss). So, I won’t be posting on a fixed schedule. Instead, whenever I have an interesting analysis that isn’t quite enough for a formal publication, a cool data visualization, or a neat tutorial on a model or algorithm—and, crucially, some spare time—I’ll share it here.</p>
<p>Speaking of which, my first post explores how to use Swiss public transport data to create a directed network. I plan to turn this into a series of blogposts, applying different network science concepts to that network.</p>
<p><em>The title image has been created by Wikimedia user Cortega9 and is licensed under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/deed.en">Creative Commons</a>.</em></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Blog</category>
  <guid>https://martinsterchi.ch/news/blog/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://martinsterchi.ch/news/blog/Blog.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>NetSci 2025, here we come</title>
  <dc:creator>Martin Sterchi</dc:creator>
  <link>https://martinsterchi.ch/news/netsci25/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>My colleague Lorenz Hilfiker and I have been accepted for a poster presentation at <a href="https://netsci2025.github.io/">NetSci2025</a>! We look forward to traveling to Maastricht (NL) this June to share our work with experts in the field.</p>
<p>Our research explores the potential of Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) for epidemic source detection—identifying the origin of an outbreak given a contact network and the epidemic states of all nodes.</p>
<p>Our (still preliminary) findings suggest that GNNs may not yet live up to their promise, as they are consistently outperformed by more traditional source detection methods. However, we have only explored a small region of the GNN design space so far, so it is too early to rule them out as a valuable tool for this problem.</p>
<p>If you’re interested, check out our abstract below—and stay tuned for a full paper on this topic!</p>
<embed src="Abstract_NetSci_2025_Sterchi_Hilfiker.pdf" width="500px" height="645px">



 ]]></description>
  <category>Conferences</category>
  <guid>https://martinsterchi.ch/news/netsci25/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://martinsterchi.ch/news/netsci25/abstract.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="89" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>New SNSF project</title>
  <dc:creator>Martin Sterchi</dc:creator>
  <link>https://martinsterchi.ch/news/snf_epi/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>In March 2024, my colleagues <a href="https://www.geography.unibe.ch/ueber_uns/personen/dr_hilfiker_lorenz/index_ger.html">Lorenz Hilfiker</a>, <a href="https://www.fhnw.ch/de/personen/matthias-templ">Matthias Templ</a>, and I submitted a project proposal to the Swiss National Science Foundation’s (SNSF) second <a href="https://www.snf.ch/en/ustwcin8DxoxxHGc/funding/projects-on-health-and-wellbeing">Health and Wellbeing Call</a>.</p>
<p>In November 2024, we received the exciting news that our project has been awarded funding! With a grant of CHF 391,938, we will be able to hire a full-time PhD student to support our research. Additionally, Lorenz will join Matthias and me at Fachhochschule Nordwestschweiz (FHNW) in 2025, starting in a part-time position.</p>
<p>Over the next four years, our team—including the PhD student—will work on developing new methods to trace the origins of epidemic outbreaks in contact networks. While researchers have been exploring epidemic source detection for about 15 years, many existing studies focus on simplified models and small networks, limiting their practical applications. Our project aims to address these challenges by pursuing two key goals:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Scalability</strong>: Developing methods that can be applied to large-scale contact networks.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Real-world applicability</strong>: Designing techniques that account for uncertainty in key parameters, making them more suitable for practical use.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Our research is not limited to human pandemics—it also has significant applications in the agricultural and livestock industries, where regulatory requirements often ensure the availability of contact data.</p>
<p>Ultimately, we hope our methods will become valuable tools for preventing future outbreaks, whether in human or veterinary health. We are thrilled to embark on this journey and look forward to the discoveries ahead!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Projects</category>
  <guid>https://martinsterchi.ch/news/snf_epi/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://martinsterchi.ch/news/snf_epi/SNF_logo_standard_office_color_pos_e.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="33" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
